<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-20T19:05:12+00:00</updated><id>https://rami-rk.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Self Attention</title><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2025/self-attention/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self Attention"/><published>2025-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2025/self-attention</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2025/self-attention/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>Most popular language models are Transformer-based and use a technique called self-attention. Self-attention differs from the attention mechanism used in RNN-based encoder-decoder models. This section builds intuition before the math.</p> <p>The primary function of self-attention is to generate context-aware vectors from the input sequence itself, rather than considering both input and output as in the RNN encoder-decoder architecture.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/attention_matrix-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/attention_matrix-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/attention_matrix-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/attention_matrix.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 1</figcaption> </figure> <p>In this example, there are 7 words in the sentence “the train left the station on time” and a 7x7 attention score matrix. The word “train” pays more attention to “station” than to other words like “on” or “the.”</p> <p>Attention scores help in understanding the contextual meaning of a word in a sentence. Here “station” is used in the context of a train station, not a gas station or bus station.</p> <p>The attention score is computed through cosine similarity (dot product), which assesses the relationship between words.</p> <p>These scores are used as weights to compute a weighted sum of all words in the sentence. When representing the word “station,” the words closely related to “station” contribute more to the sum, producing a context-aware vector.</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Note</strong> The attention vector and weights can be written as:</p> \[A(i) = \sum_{j=1}^{T_x} \alpha(i,j) x_j\] </blockquote> <p>Unfolding the equation for the word “train”:</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/unfolding_attention_vector-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/unfolding_attention_vector-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/unfolding_attention_vector-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/unfolding_attention_vector.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 1 (unfolding)</figcaption> </figure> <p>This process is repeated for every word in the sentence, yielding a new sequence of context-aware vectors.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="calculation-of-attention-weights">Calculation of Attention Weights</h2> <p>Before diving into self-attention, it helps to recall how attention is computed in RNN-based encoder-decoder models.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/context_vector-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/context_vector-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/context_vector-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/context_vector.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 2</figcaption> </figure> <blockquote> <p><strong>Recall: RNN Attention</strong></p> <p><strong>Context vector:</strong> \(C(i) = \sum_{j=1}^{T_x} \alpha_{i,j} h(j)\)</p> <p><strong>Score:</strong> \(e_{i,j} = f(S_{i-1}, h_j)\)</p> <p><strong>Attention score:</strong> \(\alpha_{i,j} = \frac{\exp(e_{i,j})}{\sum_{k=1}^{T} \exp(e_{i,k})}\)</p> </blockquote> <p>In self-attention, we remove RNN units and compute context-aware vectors from the input sequence itself. Suppose we have a sequence of feature vectors (embeddings) \(X_1, X_2, \dots, X_T\). We use dot products to compute scores and apply SoftMax.</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Self-Attention</strong></p> <p><strong>Score:</strong> \(X_i^T X_j\)</p> <p><strong>Attention score:</strong> \(\alpha_{i,j} = \text{SoftMax}(\text{score} / \text{const.})\)</p> <p><strong>Attention vector:</strong> \(A(i) = \sum_{j=1}^{T_x} \alpha_{i,j} x(j)\)</p> </blockquote> <p>Here \(h(j)\) is replaced by \(x_j\) and we call the output the “attention vector.”</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/attention_vector-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/attention_vector-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/attention_vector-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/attention_vector.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 3</figcaption> </figure> <p>Self-attention in vectorized form:</p> \[\text{SoftMax}\left(\frac{X_i^T X_j}{\text{const.}}\right) \cdot x_j \quad \text{(I)}\] <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/table_comparison-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/table_comparison-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/table_comparison-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/table_comparison.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Table 1: Comparison of self-attention and RNN-based attention</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="introducing-queries-keys-and-values">Introducing Queries, Keys, and Values</h2> <p>The formulation above has no learnable parameters. To make self-attention trainable, we introduce three weight matrices and compute Queries (Q), Keys (K), and Values (V):</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Definitions</strong></p> <p><strong>Queries:</strong> \(Q = XW^Q\)</p> <p><strong>Keys:</strong> \(K = XW^K\)</p> <p><strong>Values:</strong> \(V = XW^V\)</p> </blockquote> <p>Assume the input is a sequence with length \(T\) and embedding dimension \(d_{model}\).</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/input_data_sample-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/input_data_sample-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/input_data_sample-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/input_data_sample.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 4</figcaption> </figure> <p>Shape tracking:</p> <p>\(Q = XW^Q \rightarrow (T \times d_{model}) \cdot (d_{model} \times d_k) \rightarrow (T \times d_k)\) \(K = XW^K \rightarrow (T \times d_{model}) \cdot (d_{model} \times d_k) \rightarrow (T \times d_k)\) \(V = XW^V \rightarrow (T \times d_{model}) \cdot (d_{model} \times d_v) \rightarrow (T \times d_v)\)</p> <p>Substituting into (I), with \(\text{const.} = \sqrt{d_k}\), we get:</p> \[\text{Attention}(Q, K, V) = \text{SoftMax}\left(\frac{QK^T}{\sqrt{d_k}}\right)V \quad \text{(II)}\] <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dor_product_depiction1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dor_product_depiction1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dor_product_depiction1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dor_product_depiction1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 5</figcaption> </figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dot_product_shapes1_m-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dot_product_shapes1_m-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dot_product_shapes1_m-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dot_product_shapes1_m.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 6</figcaption> </figure> <p>Shape of \(QK^T\):</p> \[(T \times d_k) \times (d_k \times T) \rightarrow (T \times T)\] <p>Final output shape:</p> \[(T \times T) \times (T \times d_v) \rightarrow (T \times d_v)\] <p>For batch size \(N\), the shape becomes \(N \times T \times d_v\). The values of \(d_k, d_v, d_{model}\) are hyperparameters chosen to make the matrix multiplications valid.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="database-analogy-for-queries-keys-and-values">Database Analogy for Queries, Keys, and Values</h2> <p>In databases, queries retrieve data, keys identify records, and values contain the data. A similar analogy applies to self-attention Q, K, and V:</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/database_inspiration-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/database_inspiration-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/database_inspiration-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/database_inspiration.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 7</figcaption> </figure> <p>In self-attention, every word acts as a query once, while all words in the sequence act as keys. Attention weights determine which keys match a query. Values are then combined using these weights to form the attention vector.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="how-self-attention-helps-in-contextual-understanding">How Self-Attention Helps in Contextual Understanding</h2> <p>If we see the word “check” alone, it could mean different things. When we look at surrounding words like “cashed” and “bank,” we understand the context is a financial document rather than a chess move or a homework check.</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Notes</strong></p> <ul> <li>Each word attends to every other word. For \(T\) words, there are \(T^2\) attention computations.</li> <li>Q, K, and V are computed in parallel (unlike RNNs which are sequential).</li> <li>Self-attention handles long sequences better than RNNs and avoids vanishing gradients.</li> </ul> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AIML"/><category term="AIML"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From intuition to scaled dot-product attention.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[<p>May 14, 2024 We’re introducing a series of updates across the Gemini family of models, including the new 1.5 Flash, our lightweight model for speed and efficiency, and Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants. In December, we launched our first natively multimodal model Gemini 1.0 in three sizes: Ultra, Pro and Nano. Just a few months later we released 1.5 Pro, with enhanced performance and a breakthrough long context window of 1 million tokens.Developers and enterprise customers have been putting 1.5 Pro to use in incredible ways and finding its long context window, multimodal reasoning capabilities and impressive overall performance incredibly useful.We know from user feedback that some applications need lower latency and a lower cost to serve. This inspired us to keep innovating, so today, we’re introducing Gemini 1.5 Flash: a model that’s lighter-weight than 1.5 Pro, and designed to be fast and efficient to serve at scale.Both 1.5 Pro and 1.5 Flash are available in public preview with a 1 million token context window in Google AI Studio and Vertex AI. And now, 1.5 Pro is also available with a 2 million token context window via waitlist to developers using the API and to Google Cloud customers.We’re also introducing updates across the Gemini family of models, announcing our next generation of open models, Gemma 2, and sharing progress on the future of AI assistants, with Project Astra.Context lengths of leading foundation models compared with Gemini 1.5’s 2 million token capability1.5 Flash is the newest addition to the Gemini model family and the fastest Gemini model served in the API. It’s optimized for high-volume, high-frequency tasks at scale, is more cost-efficient to serve and features our breakthrough long context window.While it’s a lighter weight model than 1.5 Pro, it’s highly capable of multimodal reasoning across vast amounts of information and delivers impressive quality for its size.The new Gemini 1.5 Flash model is optimized for speed and efficiency, is highly capable of multimodal reasoning and features our breakthrough long context window.1.5 Flash excels at summarization, chat applications, image and video captioning, data extraction from long documents and tables, and more. This is because it’s been trained by 1.5 Pro through a process called “distillation,” where the most essential knowledge and skills from a larger model are transferred to a smaller, more efficient model.Read more about 1.5 Flash in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report, on the Gemini technology page, and learn about 1.5 Flash’s availability and pricing.Over the last few months, we’ve significantly improved 1.5 Pro, our best model for general performance across a wide range of tasks.Beyond extending its context window to 2 million tokens, we’ve enhanced its code generation, logical reasoning and planning, multi-turn conversation, and audio and image understanding through data and algorithmic advances. We see strong improvements on public and internal benchmarks for each of these tasks.1.5 Pro can now follow increasingly complex and nuanced instructions, including ones that specify product-level behavior involving role, format and style. We’ve improved control over the model’s responses for specific use cases, like crafting the persona and response style of a chat agent or automating workflows through multiple function calls. And we’ve enabled users to steer model behavior by setting system instructions.We added audio understanding in the Gemini API and Google AI Studio, so 1.5 Pro can now reason across image and audio for videos uploaded in Google AI Studio. And we’re now integrating 1.5 Pro into Google products, including Gemini Advanced and in Workspace apps.Read more about 1.5 Pro in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report and on the Gemini technology page.Gemini Nano is expanding beyond text-only inputs to include images as well. Starting with Pixel, applications using Gemini Nano with Multimodality will be able to understand the world the way people do — not just through text, but also through sight, sound and spoken language.Read more about Gemini 1.0 Nano on Android.Today, we’re also sharing a series of updates to Gemma, our family of open models built from the same research and technology used to create the Gemini models.We’re announcing Gemma 2, our next generation of open models for responsible AI innovation. Gemma 2 has a new architecture designed for breakthrough performance and efficiency, and will be available in new sizes.The Gemma family is also expanding with PaliGemma, our first vision-language model inspired by PaLI-3. And we’ve upgraded our Responsible Generative AI Toolkit with LLM Comparator for evaluating the quality of model responses.Read more on the Developer blog.As part of Google DeepMind’s mission to build AI responsibly to benefit humanity, we’ve always wanted to develop universal AI agents that can be helpful in everyday life. That’s why today, we’re sharing our progress in building the future of AI assistants with Project Astra (advanced seeing and talking responsive agent).To be truly useful, an agent needs to understand and respond to the complex and dynamic world just like people do — and take in and remember what it sees and hears to understand context and take action. It also needs to be proactive, teachable and personal, so users can talk to it naturally and without lag or delay.While we’ve made incredible progress developing AI systems that can understand multimodal information, getting response time down to something conversational is a difficult engineering challenge. Over the past few years, we’ve been working to improve how our models perceive, reason and converse to make the pace and quality of interaction feel more natural.Building on Gemini, we’ve developed prototype agents that can process information faster by continuously encoding video frames, combining the video and speech input into a timeline of events, and caching this information for efficient recall.By leveraging our leading speech models, we also enhanced how they sound, giving the agents a wider range of intonations. These agents can better understand the context they’re being used in, and respond quickly, in conversation.With technology like this, it’s easy to envision a future where people could have an expert AI assistant by their side, through a phone or glasses. And some of these capabilities are coming to Google products, like the Gemini app and web experience, later this year.We’ve made incredible progress so far with our family of Gemini models, and we’re always striving to advance the state-of-the-art even further. By investing in a relentless production line of innovation, we’re able to explore new ideas at the frontier, while also unlocking the possibility of new and exciting Gemini use cases.Learn more about Gemini and its capabilities. Your information will be used in accordance with Google’s privacy policy.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Done. Just one step more.
    
      Check your inbox to confirm your subscription.
    You are already subscribed to our newsletter.
    You can also subscribe with a
    different email address
    
    .
    
  Let’s stay in touch. Get the latest news from Google in your inbox.
          Follow Us
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="external-posts"/><category term="google"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Transformer Model Architecture</title><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/transformer-architecture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transformer Model Architecture"/><published>2024-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/transformer-architecture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/transformer-architecture/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>Figure 1 shows the Transformer architecture from the “Attention Is All You Need” paper (2017). The left block is the <strong>Encoder</strong> and the right block is the <strong>Decoder</strong>. This encoder-decoder architecture mirrors RNN-based seq2seq in its input-output flow, but removes recurrent components. The decoder still behaves as a causal model.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/tfr_full_archi-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/tfr_full_archi-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/tfr_full_archi-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/tfr_full_archi.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 1</figcaption> </figure> <p>The encoder sends values (V) and queries (Q) to the decoder in a cross-attention connection, allowing the decoder to focus on relevant parts of the encoded input when producing the output sequence.</p> <p>Encoders and decoders can also stand alone. BERT is encoder-only, GPT is decoder-only, and T5 combines both.</p> <p>Both blocks include Positional Encoding, Multi-Head Attention, Add &amp; Norm (skip connection + layer norm), and Feed Forward layers. The decoder uses causal (masked) attention so each token attends only to previous tokens.</p> <p><strong>Mastering the Encoder block makes the entire Transformer easier to understand.</strong></p> <hr/> <h2 id="encoder">Encoder</h2> <p>The encoder consists of Transformer blocks as shown in Fig. 2 (simplified and expanded in the right panel).</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/enc_unfolded-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/enc_unfolded-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/enc_unfolded-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/enc_unfolded.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 2</figcaption> </figure> <p>The Transformer block can be sub-divided into two main sub-layers:</p> <ul> <li>A <strong>multi-head attention</strong> sub-layer that receives queries, keys, and values.</li> <li>A <strong>feed-forward network</strong> sub-layer.</li> </ul> <p>Each sub-layer is followed by layer normalization and a residual connection. Dropout is applied before layer norm for regularization (not shown in the diagram).</p> <p>The feed-forward network is typically two linear layers with a ReLU activation in between. The encoder is formed by stacking these blocks multiple times (shown as N in Fig. 2).</p> <p>BERT (Bi-directional Encoder Representations) is an encoder-only architecture that stacks multiple transformer blocks and a prediction head, as shown in Fig. 3.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/tfr_blocks_assembed-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/tfr_blocks_assembed-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/tfr_blocks_assembed-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/tfr_blocks_assembed.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 3</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="multi-head-attention">Multi-Head Attention</h2> <p>Multi-Head Attention (MHA) runs multiple attention heads in parallel. Each head splits Q, K, and V independently, computes attention, and the results are concatenated and projected to produce the final output. This helps the model capture multiple relationships in the sequence.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/mha-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/mha-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/mha-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/mha.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 4</figcaption> </figure> <p>Shape tracking (Fig. 5):</p> <ul> <li>Input shape to each attention layer: \((T \times d_{model})\)</li> <li>Output shape after each head: \((T \times d_V)\)</li> <li>Output after concatenation: \((T \times h d_V)\)</li> </ul> <p>Final projection:</p> \[\text{Output} = \text{Concat}(A_1, A_2, \dots, A_h) W^O\] <ul> <li> \[\text{Concat}(A_1, \dots, A_h) \rightarrow (T \times h d_V)\] </li> <li> \[W^O \rightarrow (h d_V \times d_{model})\] </li> <li>Output shape: \((T \times d_{model})\)</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p><strong>Back to the initial input shape.</strong></p> </blockquote> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/mh_concat-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/mh_concat-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/mh_concat-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/mh_concat.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 5</figcaption> </figure> <p>Each head operates independently, so attention calculations are parallel.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="positional-encoding">Positional Encoding</h2> <p>Without RNNs, attention is permutation invariant, so token order is lost. Positional encoding adds order information to embeddings by injecting a unique pattern of values at each position.</p> <p>Two common approaches:</p> <ol> <li>Trainable positional embeddings (sub-class the embedding layer).</li> <li>Fixed sinusoidal encoding (as in the original paper).</li> </ol> <p>Paper formulas:</p> \[PE_{(pos,\,2i)}=\sin\!\left(\frac{pos}{10000^{2i/d_{model}}}\right)\] \[PE_{(pos,\,2i+1)}=\cos\!\left(\frac{pos}{10000^{2i/d_{model}}}\right)\] <hr/> <h2 id="causal-or-masked-attention-in-decoder-block">Causal or Masked Attention in Decoder Block</h2> <p>Decoder blocks are causal. When predicting a token, the decoder should only attend to previous tokens, not future tokens.</p> <p>For a sequence length \(T\), the attention score matrix is \(T \times T\). We enforce causality by masking the upper triangle so that attention weights are non-zero only when \(i \ge j\).</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/masking-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/masking-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/masking-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/masking.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 6</figcaption> </figure> <p>This masked attention is used inside decoder blocks. GPT-style models are decoder-only architectures built on this mechanism.</p> <p>The decoder with masked MHA is shown in Fig. 7:</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/decoder_with_masked_mha-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/decoder_with_masked_mha-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/decoder_with_masked_mha-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/decoder_with_masked_mha.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 7</figcaption> </figure> <p>The full encoder-decoder connection is shown in Fig. 8:</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/enc_dec_connection-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/enc_dec_connection-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/enc_dec_connection-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/enc_dec_connection.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 8</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="why-does-multi-head-attention-work">Why Does Multi-Head Attention Work</h2> <p>Multi-head attention lets the model learn multiple types of relationships in parallel. For example, one head might capture <em>where</em> a subject goes, while another captures <em>what</em> the subject did. This allows richer representations of sequences.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/intuition_mha-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/intuition_mha-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/intuition_mha-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/intuition_mha.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 9</figcaption> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AIML"/><category term="AIML"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From encoders to masked attention and decoders - Transformer architecture demystified.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Birth of Attention Mechanism</title><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/birth-of-attention-mechanism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Birth of Attention Mechanism"/><published>2024-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/birth-of-attention-mechanism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/birth-of-attention-mechanism/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>The onset of ChatGPT and open-source LLMs has changed how we work across industries, but transformer-based models power the magic behind BERT, GPT, and other large language models. This post is part of a series to explain Transformers step by step:</p> <ol> <li>The Birth of Attention Mechanism</li> <li>Self-Attention</li> <li>Transformer Architecture</li> </ol> <p>We start with the attention mechanism in the context of language translation using a seq2seq (encoder-decoder) architecture. In the example below, a Hindi sentence (in Devanagari) is fed into an encoder and decoded into English as “I love to eat.”</p> <p>The encoder ingests the input and computes hidden states \(h(1), h(2), \dots, h(T)\), returning a final hidden state \(h(T)\). This vector is a compressed representation of the input sequence (often called a “thought vector”) and becomes the input to the decoder.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/enc_dec_rnn-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/enc_dec_rnn-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/enc_dec_rnn-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/enc_dec_rnn.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 1</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="lets-see-the-decoder-in-detail">Lets See the Decoder in Detail</h2> <p>Every RNN unit has two sources of input: the current input and the previous hidden state. The decoder is an RNN that uses the encoder output \(h(T)\) as its initial hidden state. Its job is to decompress the input representation into the target sequence.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-goes-into-the-bottom-of-the-decoder-rnn-unit">What Goes Into the Bottom of the Decoder RNN Unit</h2> <p>At the beginning, a special token <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\&lt;SOS&gt;</code> indicates the start of the sequence. The decoder predicts the first word, feeds it back as input, and continues until it produces the end token. This is an autoregressive (causal) process. In practice, training requires paired input-output sentence data.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="problem-with-seq2seq">Problem With Seq2Seq</h2> <ol> <li>Every input sequence is compressed into a single fixed-size vector \(h(T)\). For long sentences, that vector must remember too much.</li> <li>Humans do not translate by remembering entire sentences at once; we focus on relevant parts as we go.</li> </ol> <hr/> <h2 id="to-solve-this-problem-attention-is-originated-for-seq2seq">To Solve This Problem: Attention is Originated for Seq2Seq</h2> <p>The idea is to let each output word attend to the most relevant parts of the input.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_def-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_def-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_def-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_def.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 2</figcaption> </figure> <p>Consider an input sentence (in Hindi) that translates to “I am going to play.” The list \(t_1\) contains attention values for the first output word, \(t_2\) for the second, and so on. Each list represents how much the output should focus on each input word.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_values-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_values-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_values-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_values.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 3</figcaption> </figure> <p>For the first output word, we might focus on just the first input token; later steps may focus on different or multiple input tokens. This is exactly what standard seq2seq fails to do, since each step only sees the same final encoder state.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="improved-encoder-decoder-architecture-with-attention">Improved Encoder-Decoder Architecture With Attention</h2> <p>Instead of feeding only the final encoder state to the decoder, we provide all encoder hidden states to each decoder step and learn attention weights (alphas) that determine how much each input should contribute.</p> <p>For output at time step \(t = 2\):</p> <p>\(\alpha_{2,1} \text{ is the weight on input 1}\) \(\alpha_{2,2} \text{ is the weight on input 2}\) \(\alpha_{2,3} \text{ is the weight on input 3}\) \(\alpha_{2,4} \text{ is the weight on input 4}\)</p> <p>Similarly, for output at time step \(t = 4\):</p> \[\alpha_{4,1}, \alpha_{4,2}, \alpha_{4,3}, \alpha_{4,4}\] <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/rnn_with_attention-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/rnn_with_attention-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/rnn_with_attention-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/rnn_with_attention.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 4</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="context-vector">Context Vector</h2> <p>Define the weighted combination as a context vector. For output at time step 4:</p> \[C(4) = \alpha_{4,1} h(1) + \alpha_{4,2} h(2) + \alpha_{4,3} h(3) + \alpha_{4,4} h(4)\] <p>In general:</p> \[C(i) = \sum_{j=1}^{T_x} \alpha_{i,j} h(j)\] <p>The context vector is simply the weighted sum of encoder hidden states. The weights are the attention scores.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="calculating-attention-weights">Calculating Attention Weights</h2> <p>We introduce an alignment score \(e_{i,j}\): at the \(i^\text{th}\) decoder step, how important is the \(j^\text{th}\) input word. This depends on the decoder state and the encoder hidden state:</p> \[e_{i,j} = f(S_{i-1}, h_j)\] <p>We then normalize these scores with SoftMax to form a probability distribution over input tokens:</p> \[\alpha_{i,j} = \frac{\exp(e_{i,j})}{\sum_{k=1}^{T} \exp(e_{i,k})}\] <p>The attention weight \(\alpha_{i,j}\) is the probability of focusing on the \(j^\text{th}\) input word when producing the \(i^\text{th}\) output word.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AIML"/><category term="AIML"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The evolution of attention in sequence-to-sequence models.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[<h3>External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</h3> <p>If you prefer publishing blog posts on medium.com or other external sources, starting version v0.5.0, <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">al-folio</a> lets you to display your external posts in the blog feed of your website! 🎉🎉</p> <p>Configuring external sources of super simple. After upgrading to v0.5.0, just add the following section to your _config.yml:</p> <pre>external_sources:<br />  - name: medium.com  # name of the source (arbitrary string)<br />    rss_url: <a href="https://medium.com/@al-folio/feed">https://medium.com/@&lt;your-medium-username&gt;/feed</a></pre> <p>The example above adds your medium.com blog post feed as an external source. But you can add arbitrary RSS feeds as sources.</p> <p>Any questions or suggestions? 👉 Start <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/discussions">a discussion on GitHub</a>!</p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=b60a1d241a0a" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="external-posts"/><category term="medium"/></entry></feed>