<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-11T04:10:14+00:00</updated><id>https://rami-rk.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Self Attention</title><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2025/self-attention/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self Attention"/><published>2025-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2025/self-attention</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2025/self-attention/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="overview">Overview</h3> <p>Most of the popular language models are Transformer-based architectures that use an important technique called ‘self-attention’. The ‘self-attention’ is a little different from the attention mechanism used in the RNN-based encoder-decoder model. Let’s first try to understand the intuition before delving into mathematical details and equations.</p> <p>The primary function of self-attention is to generate context-aware vectors from the input sequence itself rather than considering both input and output as in the RNN-based encoder-decoder architecture. See the example below shown in Fig. 1 (Ref. Deep Learning with Python by François Chollet).</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/attention_matrix-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/attention_matrix-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/attention_matrix-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/attention_matrix.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 1</figcaption> </figure> <p>In this example, there are 7 sequences in the sentence ‘the train left the station on time’, and we can see a 7x7 attention score matrix. For the time being, let’s say we somehow obtained these attention score values.</p> <p>According to the self-attention scores depicted in the picture, the word ‘train’ pays more attention to the word ‘station’ rather than other words in consideration, such as ‘on’ or ‘the’. Alternatively, we can say the word ‘station’ pays more attention to the word ‘train’ rather than other words in consideration, such as ‘on’ or ‘the’.</p> <p>The attention scores of each word in a sequence with all other words can be calculated, and the same is shown in the figure as a 7x7 score matrix. The self-attention model allows inputs to interact with each other (i.e., calculate the attention of all other inputs with one input).</p> <p>Attention scores help in understanding the contextual meaning of a word in a given sentence. For example, here the word ‘station’ has been used in the context of a train station, not in other contexts like a gas station or a bus station, etc.</p> <p>The attention score is computed through cosine similarity, i.e., the dot product of two-word vectors, which assesses the strength of their relationship or the degree of similarity between the compared words. There are many other mathematical aspects to consider, which will be discussed subsequently.</p> <p>These attention scores are utilized as weights for calculating the weighted sum of all the words in the sentence. For example, when representing the word ‘station’, the words closely related to ‘station’ will contribute more to the sum (including the word ‘station’ itself), while irrelevant words will contribute almost nothing. The resulting vector serves as a new representation of the word ‘station’, incorporating the surrounding context. Specifically, it includes part of the ‘train’ vector, thereby clarifying that it is, indeed, a ‘train station’.</p> <p>Let’s understand the above paragraph by writing a mathematical equation as given below, where \(A(i), \alpha(i,j)\) are weighted sum (termed as attention vector) and attention scores (weights) respectively, and individual word vector is represented by \(x_j\) . \(T_x\) represents the total number of terms in the sequence.</p> <p><strong>Note</strong> : The attention vector and weights can be written as:</p> \[A(i) = \sum_{j=1}^{T_x} \alpha(i,j) x_j\] <p>Unfolding the equation for the word “train”:</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/unfolding_attention_vector-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/unfolding_attention_vector-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/unfolding_attention_vector-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/unfolding_attention_vector.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 1 (unfolding)</figcaption> </figure> <p>This process is iterated for every word in the sentence, yielding a new sequence of vectors that encode the sentence.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="calculation-of-attention-weights">Calculation of Attention Weights</h3> <p>Before delving into the mathematical details of the self-attention mechanism, let’s revisit the equations and terms derived from the attention mechanism in RNN-based encoder-decoder architectures (as explained in my initial article: <a href="/blog/2024/birth-of-attention-mechanism/">Birth of Attention Mechanism</a> ). Although it’s not necessary, to begin with the RNN-based attention mechanism to grasp self-attention, comparing term by term would facilitate comprehension and help us understand how identical concepts are used in both.</p> <p>A conceptual diagram is shown in Fig. 2 below to depict the attention mechanism in the RNN-based encoder-decoder model, where symbols have their usual meaning.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/context_vector-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/context_vector-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/context_vector-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/context_vector.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" style=" max-width: 65%; " data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 2</figcaption> </figure> <p><strong>Recall: in the case of Attention in RNN based encoder-decoder model:</strong></p> <p><strong>Context vector:</strong> \(C(i) = \sum_{j=1}^{T_x} \alpha_{i,j} h(j)\)</p> <p><strong>Score:</strong> \(e_{i,j} = f(S_{i-1}, h_j)\)</p> <p><strong>Attention score</strong> (SoftMax of score): \(\alpha_{i,j} = \frac{\exp(e_{i,j})}{\sum_{k=1}^{T} \exp(e_{i,k})}\)</p> <h3 id="self-attention">Self-Attention</h3> <p>In Self-Attention, we get rid of RNN units and calculate the context-aware vectors from the input sequence itself. A conceptual diagram is shown in Fig. 3 below to depict the Self-attention. Suppose we have a sequence of feature vectors (embeddings) \(X_1, X_2, \dots, X_T\)., in this case, T equals 4. We can use the concept of cosine similarity, which measures sameness or relatedness, to calculate scores and finally obtain the SoftMax, which can be used in the context vector as given below.</p> <p>In the case of Self-attention, the score is cosine similarity, i.e. dot product of the input sequence with itself. Thus,</p> <p><strong>Score:</strong> \(X_i^T X_j\) [Dot product of input vector with itself.]</p> <p><strong>Attention score:</strong> \(\alpha_{i,j} = \text{SoftMax}(\text{score} / \text{const.})\) [Dividing by a constant to control the variance.]</p> <p><strong>Self-Attention vector:</strong> \(A(i) = \sum_{j=1}^{T_x} \alpha_{i,j} x(j)\)</p> <p>Here \(h(j)\) is replaced by \(x_j\) and notation is changed from <strong>C</strong> to <strong>A</strong> as we call it <strong>“Attention Vector”</strong> insted of “context vector.”</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/attention_vector-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/attention_vector-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/attention_vector-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/attention_vector.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" style=" max-width: 65%; " data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 3</figcaption> </figure> <p><strong>Self-attention in vectorized form:</strong></p> \[\text{SoftMax}\left(\frac{X_i^T X_j}{\text{const.}}\right) \cdot x_j \quad ------ \text{(I)}\] <p>Table 1 shown below presents the side-by-side comparison of Self Attention Mechanism and RNN based Attention Mechanism.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/table_comparison-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/table_comparison-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/table_comparison-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/table_comparison.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Table 1: Comparison of self-attention and RNN-based attention</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h3 id="introducing-queries-keys-and-values">Introducing Queries, Keys, and Values</h3> <p>We computed the Self-Attention vector, as derived above, based on the inputs of the vectors themselves. This means that for fixed inputs, these attention weights would always be fixed. In other words, there are no learnable parameters. This is problematic and needs to be fixed by introducing some learnable parameters that will make the self-attention mechanism more flexible and tunable for various tasks. To fulfill this purpose, three trainable weight matrices are introduced and multiplied with input Xi separately, and three new terms Queries(Q), Keys(K), and Values(V) come into the picture as given by the equations below. Vectorized implementation &amp; Shape tracking are also shown in subsequent steps.</p> <p>Assume input ‘X’ is a sequence of ‘T’ time steps or in simple words a sentence with ‘T’ words and each word is represented by an Embedding vector of dimension ‘d_model’. Fig. 4 below shows multiple sentence samples (Xi’s) in rows S1, S2, S3, and so on, and words by column as ti=1, 2, 3, …, ti=T, which is say, up to 100.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/input_data_sample-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/input_data_sample-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/input_data_sample-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/input_data_sample.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 4</figcaption> </figure> <p>Notation and dimensions are followed as per the paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.03762" target="_blank">Attention Is All You Need</a>. Table 2 of shapes and Fig. 6 are taken from this paper.</p> <p><strong>Shape of</strong> \(X \rightarrow (T \times d_{model})\)</p> <p><strong>Queries:</strong> \(Q = XW^Q\), Where \(W^Q\) is weight matrix introduced to calculate Q from X.</p> <p><strong>Keys:</strong> \(K = XW^K\), Where \(W^K\) is weight matrix introduced to calculate K from X.</p> <p><strong>Values:</strong> \(V = XW^V\), Where \(W^V\) is weight matrix introduced to calculate V from X.</p> <p><strong>Shape tracking</strong> → (shape of \(X\) ) Matrix Mult. (shape of \(W^Q\) ) → <strong>Output shape</strong></p> <p>\(Q = XW^Q \rightarrow (T \times d_{model}) \cdot (d_{model} \times d_k) \rightarrow (T \times d_k)\) \(K = XW^K \rightarrow (T \times d_{model}) \cdot (d_{model} \times d_k) \rightarrow (T \times d_k)\) \(V = XW^V \rightarrow (T \times d_{model}) \cdot (d_{model} \times d_v) \rightarrow (T \times d_v)\)</p> <p>Finally, substituting Q, K, V, and \(\text{const.} = \sqrt{d_k}\) (\(d_k\) dimensionality of the key vector) in above self-attention eqn.(I) , we get equation for attention as given below:</p> \[\text{Attention}(Q, K, V) = \text{SoftMax}\left(\frac{QK^T}{\sqrt{d_k}}\right)V \quad ------ \text{(II)}\] <p>Fig.5 below is a graphical representation of obtaining Q, K, and V from input X and feeding into equation (II) above</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dor_product_depiction1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dor_product_depiction1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dor_product_depiction1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dor_product_depiction1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 5</figcaption> </figure> <p>Above attention eqn. (II) is also termed as Scaled Dot Product Attention depicted in Fig. 6 given below.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dot_product_shapes1_m-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dot_product_shapes1_m-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dot_product_shapes1_m-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/scaled_dot_product_shapes1_m.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 6</figcaption> </figure> <p>Shape of \(QK^T\): \((T \times d_k) \times (d_k \times T) \rightarrow (T \times T)\)</p> <p>And finally, the <strong>shape of final attention output</strong>: \((T \times T) \times (T \times d_v) → (T \times d_v)\)</p> <p>If we consider a batch of \(N\) samples at a time for processing, then above shape will be: \(N \times T \times d_v\). Please note that the shapes of \(W^Q, W^K, W^V\) are chosen in a way that matrix multiplication with input <strong>‘X’</strong> is possible. The values of \(d_k, d_v , d_model\) are hyperparameters and the table of shapes above shows the values used by the author in the paper.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="database-analogy-for-queries-keys-and-values">Database Analogy for Queries, Keys, and Values</h3> <p>In the context of databases, queries are used to interact with databases to retrieve or manipulate data, keys are used to uniquely identify records and establish relationships between tables, and values are the actual data stored in the fields of a database table. The same kind of analogy exists in Self-attention Q, K, and V as well, as shown in Fig. 7 below.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/self-attention/database_inspiration-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/self-attention/database_inspiration-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/self-attention/database_inspiration-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/self-attention/database_inspiration.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 7</figcaption> </figure> <p>In this example, the word ‘check’ acts as a query, and all the words in the sequence act as keys. Attention weights find the answer to the question: ‘Which key or what are the keys that match with the query?’ by assigning different weights to the keys. Here, the word ‘check’ pays more attention to the words ‘cashed’ and ‘bank’ in the sentence, as represented by the thickness of the joining lines.</p> <p>In self-attention, every word acts as a query once, while the entire words in the sequence act as keys, and attention weights are calculated to figure out which key matches the query.</p> <p>Finally, the words (represented as vectors) are treated as values, and attention weights are used to form a weighted sum of the values, resulting in an attention vector. The attention vector for the word ‘check’ will be the weighted sum of the value vectors.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="how-self-attention-helps-in-contextual-understanding">How Self-Attention Helps in Contextual Understanding</h3> <p>In the example we looked at, we were figuring out the meaning of a word. So, if we just see the word ‘check’ by itself, it could mean different things. But when we look at the other words in the sentence, like ‘cashed’ and ‘bank’, it helps us understand that in this context ‘check’ refers to a financial document, not something like checking your homework or check in chess.</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Notes</strong></p> <ul> <li>Every word must have an attention weight with every other word, i.e., for \(T\) number of terms, there are \(T^2\) attention computations to calculate attention weights.</li> <li>Q, K, and V are calculated independently, resulting in parallelization, unlike in RNN where h(t-1) must be computed before h(t).</li> <li>Self-attention handles long sequences better than RNNs and avoids vanishing gradients.</li> </ul> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AIML"/><category term="AIML"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From intuition to scaled dot-product attention.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Transformer Model Architecture</title><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/transformer-architecture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transformer Model Architecture"/><published>2024-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/transformer-architecture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/transformer-architecture/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>Figure 1 shows the Transformer architecture from the “Attention Is All You Need” paper (2017). The left block is the <strong>Encoder</strong> and the right block is the <strong>Decoder</strong>. This encoder-decoder architecture mirrors RNN-based seq2seq in its input-output flow, but removes recurrent components. The decoder still behaves as a causal model.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/tfr_full_archi-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/tfr_full_archi-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/tfr_full_archi-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/tfr_full_archi.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 1</figcaption> </figure> <p>The encoder sends values (V) and queries (Q) to the decoder in a cross-attention connection, allowing the decoder to focus on relevant parts of the encoded input when producing the output sequence.</p> <p>Encoders and decoders can also stand alone. BERT is encoder-only, GPT is decoder-only, and T5 combines both.</p> <p>Both blocks include Positional Encoding, Multi-Head Attention, Add &amp; Norm (skip connection + layer norm), and Feed Forward layers. The decoder uses causal (masked) attention so each token attends only to previous tokens.</p> <p><strong>Mastering the Encoder block makes the entire Transformer easier to understand.</strong></p> <hr/> <h2 id="encoder">Encoder</h2> <p>The encoder consists of Transformer blocks as shown in Fig. 2 (simplified and expanded in the right panel).</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/enc_unfolded-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/enc_unfolded-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/enc_unfolded-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/enc_unfolded.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 2</figcaption> </figure> <p>The Transformer block can be sub-divided into two main sub-layers:</p> <ul> <li>A <strong>multi-head attention</strong> sub-layer that receives queries, keys, and values.</li> <li>A <strong>feed-forward network</strong> sub-layer.</li> </ul> <p>Each sub-layer is followed by layer normalization and a residual connection. Dropout is applied before layer norm for regularization (not shown in the diagram).</p> <p>The feed-forward network is typically two linear layers with a ReLU activation in between. The encoder is formed by stacking these blocks multiple times (shown as N in Fig. 2).</p> <p>BERT (Bi-directional Encoder Representations) is an encoder-only architecture that stacks multiple transformer blocks and a prediction head, as shown in Fig. 3.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/tfr_blocks_assembed-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/tfr_blocks_assembed-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/tfr_blocks_assembed-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/tfr_blocks_assembed.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 3</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="multi-head-attention">Multi-Head Attention</h2> <p>Multi-Head Attention (MHA) runs multiple attention heads in parallel. Each head splits Q, K, and V independently, computes attention, and the results are concatenated and projected to produce the final output. This helps the model capture multiple relationships in the sequence.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/mha-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/mha-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/mha-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/mha.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 4</figcaption> </figure> <p>Shape tracking (Fig. 5):</p> <ul> <li>Input shape to each attention layer: \((T \times d_{model})\)</li> <li>Output shape after each head: \((T \times d_V)\)</li> <li>Output after concatenation: \((T \times h d_V)\)</li> </ul> <p>Final projection:</p> \[\text{Output} = \text{Concat}(A_1, A_2, \dots, A_h) W^O\] <ul> <li> \[\text{Concat}(A_1, \dots, A_h) \rightarrow (T \times h d_V)\] </li> <li> \[W^O \rightarrow (h d_V \times d_{model})\] </li> <li>Output shape: \((T \times d_{model})\)</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p><strong>Back to the initial input shape.</strong></p> </blockquote> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/mh_concat-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/mh_concat-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/mh_concat-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/mh_concat.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 5</figcaption> </figure> <p>Each head operates independently, so attention calculations are parallel.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="positional-encoding">Positional Encoding</h2> <p>Without RNNs, attention is permutation invariant, so token order is lost. Positional encoding adds order information to embeddings by injecting a unique pattern of values at each position.</p> <p>Two common approaches:</p> <ol> <li>Trainable positional embeddings (sub-class the embedding layer).</li> <li>Fixed sinusoidal encoding (as in the original paper).</li> </ol> <p>Paper formulas:</p> \[PE_{(pos,\,2i)}=\sin\!\left(\frac{pos}{10000^{2i/d_{model}}}\right)\] \[PE_{(pos,\,2i+1)}=\cos\!\left(\frac{pos}{10000^{2i/d_{model}}}\right)\] <hr/> <h2 id="causal-or-masked-attention-in-decoder-block">Causal or Masked Attention in Decoder Block</h2> <p>Decoder blocks are causal. When predicting a token, the decoder should only attend to previous tokens, not future tokens.</p> <p>For a sequence length \(T\), the attention score matrix is \(T \times T\). We enforce causality by masking the upper triangle so that attention weights are non-zero only when \(i \ge j\).</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/masking-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/masking-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/masking-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/masking.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 6</figcaption> </figure> <p>This masked attention is used inside decoder blocks. GPT-style models are decoder-only architectures built on this mechanism.</p> <p>The decoder with masked MHA is shown in Fig. 7:</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/decoder_with_masked_mha-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/decoder_with_masked_mha-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/decoder_with_masked_mha-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/decoder_with_masked_mha.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 7</figcaption> </figure> <p>The full encoder-decoder connection is shown in Fig. 8:</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/enc_dec_connection-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/enc_dec_connection-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/enc_dec_connection-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/enc_dec_connection.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 8</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="why-does-multi-head-attention-work">Why Does Multi-Head Attention Work</h2> <p>Multi-head attention lets the model learn multiple types of relationships in parallel. For example, one head might capture <em>where</em> a subject goes, while another captures <em>what</em> the subject did. This allows richer representations of sequences.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/transformer/intuition_mha-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/transformer/intuition_mha-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/transformer/intuition_mha-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/transformer/intuition_mha.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 9</figcaption> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AIML"/><category term="AIML"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From encoders to masked attention and decoders - Transformer architecture demystified.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Birth of Attention Mechanism</title><link href="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/birth-of-attention-mechanism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Birth of Attention Mechanism"/><published>2024-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/birth-of-attention-mechanism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rami-rk.github.io/blog/2024/birth-of-attention-mechanism/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>The onset of ChatGPT and open-source LLMs has changed how we work across industries, but transformer-based models power the magic behind BERT, GPT, and other large language models. This post is part of a series to explain Transformers step by step:</p> <ol> <li>The Birth of Attention Mechanism</li> <li>Self-Attention</li> <li>Transformer Architecture</li> </ol> <p>We start with the attention mechanism in the context of language translation using a seq2seq (encoder-decoder) architecture. In the example below, a Hindi sentence (in Devanagari) is fed into an encoder and decoded into English as “I love to eat.”</p> <p>The encoder ingests the input and computes hidden states \(h(1), h(2), \dots, h(T)\), returning a final hidden state \(h(T)\). This vector is a compressed representation of the input sequence (often called a “thought vector”) and becomes the input to the decoder.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/enc_dec_rnn-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/enc_dec_rnn-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/enc_dec_rnn-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/enc_dec_rnn.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 1</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="lets-see-the-decoder-in-detail">Lets See the Decoder in Detail</h2> <p>Every RNN unit has two sources of input: the current input and the previous hidden state. The decoder is an RNN that uses the encoder output \(h(T)\) as its initial hidden state. Its job is to decompress the input representation into the target sequence.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-goes-into-the-bottom-of-the-decoder-rnn-unit">What Goes Into the Bottom of the Decoder RNN Unit</h2> <p>At the beginning, a special token <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\&lt;SOS&gt;</code> indicates the start of the sequence. The decoder predicts the first word, feeds it back as input, and continues until it produces the end token. This is an autoregressive (causal) process. In practice, training requires paired input-output sentence data.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="problem-with-seq2seq">Problem With Seq2Seq</h2> <ol> <li>Every input sequence is compressed into a single fixed-size vector \(h(T)\). For long sentences, that vector must remember too much.</li> <li>Humans do not translate by remembering entire sentences at once; we focus on relevant parts as we go.</li> </ol> <hr/> <h2 id="to-solve-this-problem-attention-is-originated-for-seq2seq">To Solve This Problem: Attention is Originated for Seq2Seq</h2> <p>The idea is to let each output word attend to the most relevant parts of the input.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_def-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_def-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_def-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_def.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 2</figcaption> </figure> <p>Consider an input sentence (in Hindi) that translates to “I am going to play.” The list \(t_1\) contains attention values for the first output word, \(t_2\) for the second, and so on. Each list represents how much the output should focus on each input word.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_values-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_values-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_values-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/attention_values.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 3</figcaption> </figure> <p>For the first output word, we might focus on just the first input token; later steps may focus on different or multiple input tokens. This is exactly what standard seq2seq fails to do, since each step only sees the same final encoder state.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="improved-encoder-decoder-architecture-with-attention">Improved Encoder-Decoder Architecture With Attention</h2> <p>Instead of feeding only the final encoder state to the decoder, we provide all encoder hidden states to each decoder step and learn attention weights (alphas) that determine how much each input should contribute.</p> <p>For output at time step \(t = 2\):</p> <p>\(\alpha_{2,1} \text{ is the weight on input 1}\) \(\alpha_{2,2} \text{ is the weight on input 2}\) \(\alpha_{2,3} \text{ is the weight on input 3}\) \(\alpha_{2,4} \text{ is the weight on input 4}\)</p> <p>Similarly, for output at time step \(t = 4\):</p> \[\alpha_{4,1}, \alpha_{4,2}, \alpha_{4,3}, \alpha_{4,4}\] <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/rnn_with_attention-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/rnn_with_attention-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/rnn_with_attention-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/birth-of-attention-mechanism/rnn_with_attention.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 4</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="context-vector">Context Vector</h2> <p>Define the weighted combination as a context vector. For output at time step 4:</p> \[C(4) = \alpha_{4,1} h(1) + \alpha_{4,2} h(2) + \alpha_{4,3} h(3) + \alpha_{4,4} h(4)\] <p>In general:</p> \[C(i) = \sum_{j=1}^{T_x} \alpha_{i,j} h(j)\] <p>The context vector is simply the weighted sum of encoder hidden states. The weights are the attention scores.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="calculating-attention-weights">Calculating Attention Weights</h2> <p>We introduce an alignment score \(e_{i,j}\): at the \(i^\text{th}\) decoder step, how important is the \(j^\text{th}\) input word. This depends on the decoder state and the encoder hidden state:</p> \[e_{i,j} = f(S_{i-1}, h_j)\] <p>We then normalize these scores with SoftMax to form a probability distribution over input tokens:</p> \[\alpha_{i,j} = \frac{\exp(e_{i,j})}{\sum_{k=1}^{T} \exp(e_{i,k})}\] <p>The attention weight \(\alpha_{i,j}\) is the probability of focusing on the \(j^\text{th}\) input word when producing the \(i^\text{th}\) output word.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AIML"/><category term="AIML"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The evolution of attention in sequence-to-sequence models.]]></summary></entry></feed>